Speaker: Here’s a solid gold piece of advice:
be wary of anyone offering you solid gold pieces of advice.
The friend who advises you to, say,
stay in your relationship or leave your job may well be looking out for you,
but she’s inescapably looking out for herself, too, whether she realizes it or not.
Maybe she thinks her own marriage is not perfect, and that you, too, should accept a similar situation.
Maybe she adores your company so much she could never recommend a career step
that might involve your leaving town.
Moreover, research suggests that people will generally advise you to act more cautiously
than they would act themselves in a similar situation
– perhaps because they don’t want it on their conscience
if you take a daring leap and fall flat on your face.
There’s a happy flip side to this, though, for parents, teachers, managers,
and anyone else who finds themselves in the position of needing to motivate others:
far better than giving them advice is to give them the opportunity to give advice.
That’s the conclusion of a new study by psychologists at the Universities of Chicago and Pennsylvania,
who found that American middle-school pupils were much more enthusiastic about doing their homework
after dispensing advice on the topic to younger children than after receiving advice from teachers.
This motivational effect lasted weeks and was also observed among adults
who were attempting to lose weight, save money, control their temper, or find a job.
Teach a man to fish and he’ll know how to fish – but get him to teach others how to fish,
and he might actually do some fishing.
This result isn’t all that surprising, I suppose,
when you consider how flattering it feels to be invited to give advice.
Faced with a challenge, we tend to assume we need to seek advice in order to
obtain more knowledge about how to proceed; yet the truth, very often,
is that we know exactly what we need to do – we just lack the confidence to do it.
The act of giving advice reacquaints us with the knowledge we already possess,
which instils confidence, which motivates action.
In fact, there are few bigger compliments you can pay another person than to ask,
preferably sincerely, for their advice.
As Benjamin Franklin, politician and founding father of the USA,
famously observed, to ingratiate yourself with someone,
it’s better to ask for a favour than to perform one:
the favour-doer will come to think of you as the decent and likeable sort for whom they do favours.
The same surely applies to advice: rather than giving it, ask for it.